hello everyone this is Frankie Freitas
and welcome to another week of Holo talk
for the week of May 21st 2000. welcome
back I was away for a number of weeks
and didn't have a chance to update the
show in fact uh was only back here in
the studio maybe about in a few days out
of three weeks uh on the road doing
different things also down Washington DC
with the Smithsonian so we're back here
it's great to be back great to have
another Holo talk up and uh hopefully uh
usually uh whole talk ends Memorial Day
and is off the summer from Memorial Day
through Labor day but I'm hoping to
maybe be able to continue whole talk
through the summer what what do you
think would you like to hear Hall talk
through summer send me an email and let
me know and instead of going off the air
Memorial Day what we'll do is just
continue uh producing shows throughout
the summer I'm going to try and get
Michelle Roy in here this week as many
of you are aware Michelle was with me
down at the Smithsonian at the hershon
is specifically and
I'd like to get her in the studio and do
a show on both of our feelings on what
it was like to present holography at an
art venue my background with what lasers
and photography is with science and
technology so it's always interesting
when I have the opportunity of going in
and doing
for people who have an artistic interest
in holography as well and there are
differences and we'd like to do a show
to tell you what some of those
differences are some observations we've
made and where we think holography
strong points are with both its Science
and Technology
background all it's also its artistic
background as well our guest this week
is Doris Villa and I would like to point
out before you listen to the show that
this was recorded a couple weeks ago
before we started out on our road trips
and I haven't had a chance of getting
the show up it's going up now the only
thing is Doris mentions going away to
Germany to do some work and when you
hear that you'll be under the impression
that she's leaving for Germany when in
actuality this is recorded earlier and
she's back from Germany now so keep that
in mind when you're listening to the
interview
so welcome back again and let's move on
to the interview with dorisville if
you'd like to hear Holo talk continue
through the summer please send me an
email let me know if I get enough emails
to tell me that they'd like to uh that
you'd like to hear the show so I'll
continue to do them if not then we'll
say adios and see you in the uh in the
fall so here's the interview with Doris
Fila thanks for tuning in see you next
week
foreign
hello Doris how are you fine I wanted to
switch to the other phone so I can speak
a little bit more freely how are you I'm
doing good how are you good good good
give me a sec okay all right that sounds
good that sounds okay to you yeah it's a
different sound than the other phone but
I think it'll work okay good you know I
was on your website and I've been
following a lot of your work through the
different Publications over the years
like through holist fear and wavefront
and some of the other ones and to tell
you the truth after being on your
website and seeing all the things that
you've done I'm in a loss of where to
even start with you
well that is really sweet I'm very
honored yeah I I've been busy yeah when
did you get started in holography I
thought in 1979 and in a way I kind of
date how I started much earlier than
that
having done work with Littman
photography we're creating Whitman
photographs in provincial Mexico was
your background in photography and
videography
um actually I started drawing oh okay
I'm a classic artist background and
um yeah that was how I got started what
moved you on to holography
well um when I was living and working at
the University of Veracruz in Mexico I
started working with stereophotography
okay and a lot of print making
alternative techniques where we would
improvise our own technology and we'd
know
build our own graphic arts cameras
getting the lenses ground at the local
optician and wow mix up our own photo
silk screen Emulsion starting to sound
familiar you were involved with a lot of
the technology as well
yeah I've always believed that artists
have more can make a much more
interesting statement with the medium if
they get their hands in the middle of it
well you find excuse me even in the
field of Photography that a lot of
artists try to stay away from the
technology end of it well it can be
distracting and I really understand and
respect artists that want to avoid
getting so Tech heavy that they lose
sight of
like a mental and emotional message that
they want to communicate yeah I really
understand it it just
with my work and the way I work I need
to be shifting hats all the time
I couldn't have made those big Holograms
without being able to do it myself as
like directly intervening with the plate
all the time
so I needed to understand what the
fraction efficiencies had to be in order
to get that big and operate with a
coherence length use the spherical
aberration as a way to make stories play
out at different positions rather than
different moments in time is there a
reason why you chose to do I would I
would imagine most if not all of your
work is white light transmission
Holograms is there a reason for that
well mostly because the transmission
holograph allowed me to break scale I've
done some color work and reflection in
fact one of the biggest compliments I've
gotten is my God your reflection colors
look like your transmission
colors because I really got into the
tech and how to narrow the band of
reconstruction you know what a lot of
other people have done in in reflection
but just have been able to tune it to
suit and
feel that my work already has what are
some of the projects that you would look
back on and want to tell to the
listeners about
um
all of them right yeah of course which
they can see at your website and we do
have a link to Doris website right on
the hollow talk page so if you go back
on the whole talk page and click on the
link it will take you right over to her
website which is just loaded loaded with
years worth of work and papers and
research papers and everything yeah you
know it's really interesting because of
the one of the greatest things for me
about being involved in holography has
been the number of people the range of
people have been able to meet
and the kinds of cross-discipline
jumping I've been able to do
really give a lot of room
um for my imagination all kinds of
technical imagination as well as
aesthetic yeah I I guess one of the
things that has been really uh fruitful
for me in recent years has been
combining holography with other
Electronic media
and it started with a piece in 92 that I
was able to do in Germany where I had a
hologram of fire in a store window
and was Illuminating it with the live
signal of the seat of people passing by
so as they walk by you they saw their
own seat at eye level
and they were walking through the Flames
which was of course the holographic
explains which could never burn them but
a metaphor for passing through a trial
of fire or a proof of Purity and here
they were just Shopper wow and so I like
that a lot and that gave me a lot of
jumping off territory for mixing
projected imagery when you would mix the
medium did you find that you did that
more because you felt there were
limitations in holography and you were
able to move Beyond those limitations by
mixing other media in yes very much so I
mean the presence of the three
dimensions of holography made me crave
the the fourth time so I really wanted
to be able to make that happen and
breathe a little life into the
three-dimensional form of holography
you've been teaching as well in the past
do you still run workshops and things
now in New York well I haven't had any
requests for that uh every so often I'm
asking a lecture to school which I love
to do that I'm really I get to indulge
my hands side of Myself by standing up
in front of students and talking to them
and and I one of the things that I I
have happiest about is that I've been
able to get a sense of humor if I can
say that to infuse my work because I've
had a kind of appeasing relationship
with science but it's great but it just
doesn't go quite far enough well I like
a sense of humor
glad to hear it yeah so yeah that's uh
so I like talking to groups about that
but I um I'm not getting a lot of
requests for holographic type teaching
right now wow I find that surprising in
New York City I am too no well you know
we also have a couple of very talented
people well that are you know open to
dance like this teaching yeah
one school and
running his teaching as part of his
practice and goes after that more
aggressively I'm getting more offers for
projects and shows but many of them
overseas yeah
um what's with that well you know what
are you going to say you know
I know they used to say a prophet is
never recognized in their own land but I
think a prophet is never turned in one's
own land you know I don't understand I
just was I'm going to Germany in fact on
Friday to finish up a major project with
children's interactive theater I know we
should always have a global outlook on
everything but I always feel that we
should take more pride in people within
the United States that are doing great
work and we don't well one of the things
that that happens in New York
particularly is the art world is uh
driving force and the art world is
Believe It or Not somewhat conservative
in terms of media and so there was a
certain point at which I decided that I
was going to keep making work but I was
not going to try to show it in the
traditional Gallery settings and once
you try to you break out of that mold
even though supposedly the avant-garde
is always testing limits you find that
you really have to look to people that
respect a cultural tradition and in the
states it's
the art world is still quite Market
driven
so you just have to say Okay so who's
interested
I am really working very hard on getting
more things going here in the coming
year how do you feel women are
represented in photograph as far as
people working in the field compared to
other Ventures
yes yes with a little little tiny
thought attached to it okay um
into artists and male artists I think
there's a nice 50 50 blend
um but the women in the in the Raw
technical
and Commercial Fields that's dominated
by men again yeah
um but um even among the artists if you
were to say okay who has or has had
their own Labs the women normally use
other people's facilities that's why I
say yes but I mean I think
here and it's really tough to make
gender generalization yeah but the women
often though have had really Innovative
youth of holography in space so that
they will take and do something with the
Hologram in the environment it's shown
in or a context for it yeah that the men
have more gone for a classic approach
and like I said I'm real cautious about
generalizing that I can think of some
real notable exceptions on both sides of
these success but
um yeah I think
what women have have well they may have
not been empowered to invest in that the
tech so much
certainly in terms of taking aesthetic
risks Within
right out there if not at the edge so I
have a lot of admiration for that I've
been speaking with someone at spie I'm
very sorry I can't remember their name
right now but our emails have been going
back and forth they just started a group
of women in Optics and they're very
interested in the holography programs
that I put together especially with the
shoebox logography that uses little
diode lasers to create Holograms so
we're looking to get a few programs
started at the educational level to show
female school students what's available
not just with holography but with lasers
and photonics in general well that
sounds terrific yeah yeah I mean let me
know if I can be of any help oh
absolutely yes yeah absolutely you know
I'm in the freelance mode I'm always
interested in cookouts games yeah that's
great now you have your own facilities
right yes I have
um I have a basement the 1200 square
foot basement with two five foot by 10
foot isolation tables next time you come
to New York please come by yes yes I'm
going to do that when are you coming
back from Germany uh I'll be back May
1st oh okay I'm actually going to be
showing Holograms in Mexico opening the
first tune I'm going back to that same
place I used to work why don't you give
some information to it because you know
on the net we have people that listen
from Germany as well so why don't you
give a little information about your
work that you're going over for in
Germany and also the Mexican uh show as
well great yeah
project in Germany is an interactive
children's theater installation at any
Max in bond which is an experimental
media art group and they have a
interesting space part of a Cineplex
so there you know you can imagine 12
Theaters in a Cineplex 11 of them are
showing movies and the 12th one is
having this stage where the children
walk in through a room and on either
side of them are these uh 10 foot high
by 13 feet long
greens they're like pages of a book
three on each side of them
semi-transparent and they are basically
walk into their book ship and at the
group there are interactions are
registered and they pick their way to a
journey to a place and they look for the
figures which are made up all of
triangles and as soon as they act
together these triangles swarm around
them in real-time animation reflecting
their the group dynamic of the triangles
forming and flocking in the same way
that they move
so it's very interesting on a number of
levels well it just drives me nuts that
you don't see anything like that here
well I hope to be getting a version that
can run here yeah not maybe not quite
quite physical
but uh but certainly with all the
computer animation we can do that and
I'm calling it
um pseudograms or two and a half D
because it's basically 2D
information but it's being projected
onto these layered screens which as they
move
flying in this long graceful motion as
the kids make their way through their
Adventure wow and and there's some sort
of
uh quad bike 3D in the forming of the
triangle that's really great they scream
a vowel and these figures you know could
be a monster or a bat or a shark made up
out of triangles and they go B and it
flies apart it's great and it's a real
interesting I think
um because getting a group to work
together as a team is
the metaphor we're going towards in this
Century because we've come out of very
hierarchical
path we're coming to work as play play
as work exactly and the team approach
for leadership functions are still there
but they rotate and in a much different
and consensus is the way to make a
decision rather than arbitrary obeying I
I think this is going to be and
especially if you think of the
historical implications of asking German
children to work as a group they're
shifting leadership roles this is a very
very big oh yeah yeah exactly yeah I see
that so it's it's a it's a riot and so
you can link to there's a Shockwave
example of what her game looks like on
my website
and that's a nice website do you do that
yourself why thank you yes I did with
the help of a student intern sure those
Graphics are mine and all those uh the
lamination Clips yeah I was all over
that today oh good good yeah it's a big
fun I've had a great time doing it and
um yeah and with the web it's just been
such a resource for us I I've believed
since I got involved with photography
that we were headed towards the age of
energy and information and the web just
prove it yeah every time yeah
right now I have posted just for my
working colleague for a fight which is
is private but allows them to see the
storyboards for the improvements that
we're making for the game that I'm going
over there yeah that's that's a nice
aspect of the web as well for
collaboration you know across distances
you know work collaboration yeah and
then what's coming up in Mexico well
Mexico is oh actually let me see if I
can
for that it it
in Veracruz Mexico every year for the
last nine years
Professor Miguel sanat of the University
of Veracruz is hosted what he calls June
the month of Photography and it's a
Statewide series of exhibitions last
year there were 28 shows around the
state of Photography from historic
figures
to contemporary
and he invited me to the honored guest
this year so I will be showing a
holographic installation of three large
panels
and
um and and several smaller works and
some projections and what is the turnout
for these the events that you do
overseas you find out that it's pretty
well packed well it depends on the place
if you're part of a festival in Berlin
then you can't keep them out of the door
and uh in some of the smaller places
it's not so large but you find that the
fall it's a very different attitude
there are you you find people that see
your work and three four five years
later they come back to you say I saw
your work and I want you to come and do
something now of course in this country
we're also
you know found by 15 minutes of same
conscious that if you don't
you know if you don't close it right
there that's right it's gotten you and
they've moved on yeah whereas uh I've
had people invite me to a festival where
they fly me over and sponsor an
installation
and they say oh we wanted to do this
since
yeah I was thinking about the imagery
that you were talking about with your
installation in Germany and I was
thinking that that were done here I
don't think you could do that without
including Burgers and Fries somehow in
that you know what I mean I'm telling
you it's a very different thing yeah
it's a very different thing but I'm
working on some possibilities too
I mean as as computers get faster and
more portable you want to get your lab
up and running in New York now or is it
up and running now well you know all the
physical equipment is there
unfortunately at the moment my laser is
down as I told you and this is what I've
been talking with you about your diode
lasers I'm very excited about that
possibility I have two big fat lasers
and um you know both of them need new
tubes
we're talking about thousands of dollars
replace it yeah I don't know I think
those days are coming to a close well
you know that would be nice I've never
thought it just never made sense to me
that it should be so painful painful
with a lot of things it's been a very
arduous kind of medium to pursue
and I really believe it had to get
simpler well your work is beautiful the
the only time I've had a chance to see
your work was at the Museum of
Photography in New York you do very
abstract work and just the way that the
layers are on there and how the motion
and how things interact with one another
as you move around the Holograms is
phenomenal oh thanks yeah I like to
think of them as stories that are played
out in space yeah all this time so that
the physical position of the viewer
forces them or allows them to make their
own Discovery sequence and that's what
makes it possible for them to
weave a story out of a framework of
possibilities and that's where my
teasing relationship with science has
come in I I started out in 88 making
things no 87 making things where it was
uh chart snaps and diagrams of food
scientific phenomena so it was the chart
of the space-time sex money continuum
you know because space and time are one
thing but we know Sex and Money fit in
there space and time I have a lot of
yeah Sex and Money I don't know you know
you hear what I'm saying but maybe if
you had more money you'd have more time
yeah and then you never know and if I
had more space I'd have more sex
that could be I don't know I just I have
to say Einstein was partly right he
needed to expand the emotional Horizons
a little bit and some of the others were
the diagnosis of an existential headache
and the overview of the free guilt
economy that was he said and she said so
those are facing panels so the when the
Observer stands between them they have
to look or listen to one parent or the
other they're basically the Observer
child in between the two so you can see
the physical
presence or movement of the person in
the space makes a big difference in
terms of playing out a story which is
what I think we do with our lives it
amazes me how artists minds work because
basically what my brain thinks about is
resistors and transistors and chips and
how to get diodes to work and how to do
this the technical end of it and it's
fascinating just to listen to what
people would do with the technology I
mean I have creative thought but nothing
like what you're describing well I think
creativity has a million billion forums
I think we're we're all the time
creating yeah trying to make sense out
of our lives in the world
and having some fun with it yeah any new
projects that you're planning on in the
future something with the center for the
holographic Arts well I have a residency
there now and we're in the process of
shooting I'm actually making a new piece
of them which will be the newest
holographic piece in a while so I'm
really thrilled about that
I'm delighted with the concept and
it's going to be very exciting
um
just uh
yeah I'm looking forward to getting my
lab up and running I'm hopefully with
some of those bio Blazers yeah that
would be cool and uh
yeah just things keep coming up so keep
looking at my website I'll keep people
posted there when are you leaving for
Germany I'm leaving on Friday evening
this Friday yeah okay and I'll be back
May 1st but they want me to go again in
May and then at the end of May I please
go we go to Mexico so well I was
thinking you know you might be able to
listen to the show before you go but hey
this is the internet you're in Germany
you can listen to it in Germany that's
right so what am I thinking yeah that's
the beauty of it when is it on it'll go
up Sunday night at around nine o'clock
Eastern time and then it stays up you
know it's a real audio file 24 hours a
day seven days a week and just go into
the website and click on the link and uh
real audio will start and you can listen
to the program anywhere in the world
hollowworld.com yeah and there's three
years of programs on there as well
with a lot of different people involved
with photography so if you ever have a
chance to sit back with a cup of coffee
or a cup of tea when you're home some
night you want to hear what some of the
other people have said over the last
three years uh you know oh that's
wonderful
congratulate you on what you're doing I
think it's the
remarkable yeah well you're doing
remarkable work too so as long as we all
keep doing what we're doing we'll keep
moving ahead I think so yeah
well thank you very much for being on
the show you're welcome and give Lillian
a kiss from me and I'll get a chance to
meet both of you once again when I come
into New York yes absolutely yeah give a
little notice if you can absolutely yeah
you're welcome to fill up all right all
right take care bye